Register of the Darren Kew Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Darren Kew papers
1999
99037
Kew, Darren.
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers are comprised of sound recordings, transcripts of interviews, notes, an election observer manual, memoranda, and election campaign literature, relating to presidential elections in Nigeria in 1999. Use copies of sound recordings available.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Darren Kew was born in 1969. He holds a B.A. from Notre Dame University along with a Master of Law and Diplomacy (MALD) and PhD from the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Kew is the executive director of the Center for Peace, Democracy and Development and associate professor of conflict resolution at the University of Massachusetts, Boston, where he studies the relationship between conflict resolution methods and democratic development in Africa. Much of his work focuses on the role of civil society groups in this development. Kew is also an author of numerous works on Nigerian politics and conflict resolution.
As a recognized authority on Nigerian politics and society, Kew has worked with numerous agencies, including the United Nations, United States Agency for International Development, the U.S. State Department, various non-governmental organizations, and the Carter Center. In 1999 Kew was a member of the Carter Center-National Democratic Institute observation delegation sent to Nigeria to observe the Nigerian presidential elections.
Scope and Content of Collection
The bulk of the materials in this collection were gathered by Darren Kew during his time as a member of the Carter Center-National Democratic Institute observation delegation sent to Nigeria to observe the 1999 presidential elections. The materials encompass sound recordings, documents provided to members of the observation delegation, transcripts of National Assembly and presidential election interviews, correspondence, and notes, found in the Delegation materials.
The Sound recordings contain interviews conducted by Darren Kew and an unidentified interviewer. The interviews focus on the post-election reactions of voters, research fellows, government officials, and professors. In addition there are individual interviews conducted by Darren Kew with leading members of the All People's Party (APP) and Alliance for Democracy (AD) political parties.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 2 series: Delegation materials and Sound recordings.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Elections--Nigeria.; Phonotapes.
Collection Contents
- Delegation materials, 1999 (Box 1)
  Included are transcripts of election-day interviews conducted with voters, a delegation packet containing election observer manual, election background material, memoranda, operational materials, and documents from the deployment kit used by each member in the field.
  Arranged by document type.
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Memoranda, 1999 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Delegation packet, 1999 (Folder 1: 3-4)
  - Deployment kit, 1999 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Transcripts of National Assembly election interviews, 1999 (Folder 1: 6-7)
  - Transcripts of presidential election interviews, 1999 (Folder 1: 8-9)
  - Polling center directories, circa 1999 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Handwritten note, circa 1999 (Folder 1: 11)
- Sound recordings, 1999 (Box 2)
  The recordings include reactions from Nigerian voters on the streets during election week, post-election interviews with Olu Falae, the presidential candidate for the joint platform of the Alliance for Democracy (AD) and the All People's Party (APP); Dr. Saka Balogun, a founding member of the APP; and Dr. Olajumore a presidential aspirant for the APP and former member of the United Nigeria Congress Party.
  Arranged in three groups: Nigerian elections, Presidential election interviews, and Individual interviews.
  - Nigerian elections, 2-4 March 1999 (Folder 2)
    Use copy reference number: 99037_a_0003740
    Darren Kew conducts post-election interviews with research fellows, government officials, and professors about their thoughts and impressions of the newly elected president, Olusegun Obasanjo. Tapes 1-3. In English.
    - Interviews with Dr. Cyril Obi, George Ehusani, and M.H. Kukah, 1999 (Folder 2)
      Interviews address such topics as the connection between oil and transitions in power, how the rift between the civil society groups and the political parties can be bridged, the emergence of class-based politics, voting patterns based on personalities rather than ideologies, "cash and carry politics," accountability of the new government, the role of the church, and corruption.
    - Interviews with Clement Nwankwo, Aboo Oyediran, and Tilli Adebajo, 1999 (Folder 2)
      Interviews address such topics as the formation of the Transition Monitoring Group (TMG), expectations of what will change under Obasanjo, what Nigeria will look like in four years, and election thoughts from a business perspective.
    - Conclusion of the Tilli Abebajo interview, and finishes with Dr. Frank Enemuo, 1999 (Folder 2)
      Addresses such topics as how business was conducted in Nigeria prior to Obasanjo's election, how corruption can be managed, the use of privatization, the context behind the electoral results, the dichotomy in representation between Nigerians in the north and Nigerians in the south, how easterners have viewed the election process, and what will change under the new government.
  - Presidential election interviews, 20-27 February 1999 (Folder 2)
    Use copy reference number: 99037_a_0003746
    The recordings document interviews that solicit election reactions from Nigerian voters on the streets during election week. Assorted reporters ask a cross-section of Nigerians for their opinions on the election: Whether they have confidence in the new government, why they supported a particular party, what they expect from the government, and whether there were any irregularities in the election process. Tapes 1-2. In English.
  - Individual Interviews, 1999 (Folder 2)
    - Interview with Dr. Saka Balogun, 1999 (Folder 2)
      Use copy reference number: 99037_a_0003751
      Dr. Saka Balogun, a founding member of the All People's Party (APP) in Nigeria, is interviewed concerning the growth of the nascent APP following the 1999 Nigerian elections. The unidentified interviewer questions Dr. Balogun on the party's preparation for the 1999 election, the cost of holding an election, the election results and APP's defeat, the choice of a presidential candidate, the position of the party post-election, and the projected status of the party eight years in the future.
    - Interview with Olu Falae, 1999 (Folder 2)
      Use copy reference number: 99037_a_0003753
      Olu Falae was the presidential candidate for the joint platform of the Alliance for Democracy (AD) and the All People's Party (APP) in the 1999 Nigerian elections. The majority of the tape's content is unintelligible due to the poor sound quality.
    - Interview with Dr. Olajumore, 1999 (Folder 2)
      Use copy reference number: 99037_a_0003757
      Dr. Olajumore, a presidential aspirant for the All People's Party (APP) and former member of the United Nigeria Congress Party, is interviewed about the post-election results. The unidentified interviewer questions Dr. Olajumore on his decision to join the APP rather than the other political parties that were created in the wake of General Sani Abacha's death, how the APP lost the election to the People's Democratic Party (PDP), how money has influenced the election, why he has abandoned the APP for the PDP, why an alliance with the other parties was not established, and whether he is still looking forward to contesting the presidency.
  - Open reel tape copies, 1999 (Folder 2: Reels 1-8)
    Transferred from the original sound recordings on compact sound cassettes listed above.